<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Decimas 5, Sermo 10 [U.S.A. Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#HenrichBullinger">Henrich Bullinger</author>
        <editor>Dr. Jeffrey C. Witt</editor>
        <editor>Ema-Joanne M. Brauchler </editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Decimas 5, Sermo 10 [London 1587 Transcription]</title>
          <date when="2020-05-21">May 21, 2020</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"
              >Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref></p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="L" n="cod-u2dgeg">London 1587</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0"
        url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2019-06-20" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#L" n="30"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW">
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e98">
          <!--1112.xml-->
          <!-- 1082.xml for me --> This sermon will discuss the institutions that make up each part
          of the Church of God. It will discuss schools, disbursement of ecclesiastical goods and
          money, and the use or abuse of fame within the Church context. It will discuss how to
          chastise and correct Ministers of local parishes, and global Church leaders. The sermon
          will also discuss women in the context of the Church, whether they are virgins, married
          women, widows, or nuns. The sermon will discuss monks, nuns, and church leaders. It will
          also discuss how to treat the sick, how to celebrate a funeral and how to bury a member of
          the parish. The tenth sermon defines the primitive church and analyzes what current
          religious practices do and do not belong in the original church established by Jesus
          Christ, and the original Apostles and Disciples. This sermon discusses the necessity to
          return to the simplicity established by the structures and practices of the primitive
          church. <cb ed="#L" n="a"/> There are a few certain things that remain true which I will
          expound to you dearly beloved. These things pertain to the Church, and the preservation of
          its ministry. There are certain ordinances that the Church established that do not match
          the institution of the primitive church. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e138"> In the <ref>last sermon of this decade</ref>, if the Lord
          gives me the grace to speak, I intend to briefly convey this information. God did not
          burden his church with many laws and institutions, but he did send down a few easily
          understood and simply numbered laws. These original laws were not costly, confusing, or
          long. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e156"> In the past when the Lord commanded costly and extravagant
          worship from his people, he did not intend to add or take from the pleasure of men, or to
          otherwise bleed men other than the way that he appointed. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e178">
          <!--1112.xml-->
          <cb ed="#L" n="b"/> Who would think that after abolishing these exorbitant laws, the Lord
          would deliver extravagant laws and infinite requirements to the Church of the new people?
          The covetous pastors, the estates of the church, and monstrous common superstition among
          the people made the church have extravagant laws and institutions to fulfill their unjust
          wants. Let us remember that the Lord our God instituted few laws and institutions in his
          church. These few requirements are necessary. However, we should know that the church is
          not over-burdened with traditions and institutions that do not come from God himself. The
          Church of God is lavish in her simplicity if she keeps the few institutions of her God. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e233"> The principal points of the church’s godliness are the
          sincere teaching of the laws, the teachings of the prophets, Christ and his apostles,
          faithful prayer offered to God through Christ, a devout and lawful administration, and
          recipience of Christ’s sacraments. These principal points are examined throughout the
          Decades. <!-- 1083 --> Charity, the communicating of riches and services is also a
          principal point of the church’s godliness. We have already discussed charity in the
            <ref>first decade</ref>, and we will further discuss it in this sermon. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e278"> In the <ref>Acts of the Apostles</ref>, <name>Luke</name>
          does not mention anything besides the few principals of godliness that we mentioned when
          describing the faithful primitive Church of Christ. The faithful, primitive Church of
          Christ was created by the original Apostles and it was upon the foundation of the
          principal points of godliness. According to <name>Luke</name> in the <ref>Acts of the
            Apostles</ref>, <quote>“They were continuing in the doctrine of the Apostles, and in
            communicating, and in breaking of bread and in prayer.” </quote> These few points
          comrpise true godliness. The following institutions and new traditions have joined the
          ecclesiastical ministry and contribute to the church’s godliness. Christian schools, for
          example, teach the principal points of godliness, and they bring forth an increase of
          prophets and ministers of the church. Most first world nations recognize that without
          schools, nations cannot produce and maintain kingdoms or commonwealths. <name>Moses</name>
          in the <ref>book of Genesis</ref>, and <name>Strabo</name> in his <ref>17th book of
            Geography</ref> report that the Egyptians established the most famous colleges for
          priests and philosophers. <name>Samuels</name>’s <ref>Holy Histories</ref> mention that
          the most noblemen throughout the world traveled to Egypt to obtain wisdom.
            <name>Plato</name> is said to be the first chief and principal philosopher. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e374"> In the <ref>book of Kings</ref>, it is thoughtfully
          written that <name>Salomon</name> excelled the wise men of Egypt in wisdom. Not only the
          Egyptians, but also the Palestinians who were a nation famous for… <!--1113.xml-->
          <cb ed="#L" n="b"/> war, but still had wise priests of whom they asked council in times of
          doubt. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e414">
          <name>Daniel</name> witnessed that the Babylonians, the Medes and the Persians also had
          famous schools. These schools produced Magi, which are known as wise men, who are known in
          all parts of philosophy. I do not need to discuss the Greeks and the Romans since everyone
          is aware of the famous city of Athens because so many learned men talk about it. Athens
          was also home to good colleges of priests and prophets. Omitting foreign examples, let us
          examine local ecclesiastical school models. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e454"> God gave his people absolute happiness in the form of a
          commonwealth, kingdom, and distributed schools throughout 48 towns in Switzerland. The
          towns called Levites 'Levitical' because of their philosophy. He consecrated the Levitical
          Tribe and made them priests and scholars. It wasn’t unlawful for gentlemen of other Tribes
          to study philosophy or wisdom, but the Levites were particularly appointed to holy studies
          because the Tribe later produced <name>Clay</name> and <name>Daniel</name>, two of the
          most intelligent men of the tribe of Juda, thus fulfilling the prophecy. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e487"> Other Tribes have produced a singuluar kind of knowledge.
          Those towns that specialized in one discipline were called Levitical and priestly, not
          only because priests lived there, but also because they had synagogues in the town. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e517">. <!--1114.xml-->
          <!-- 1084 -->
          <pb ed="#L" n="1114-"/>
          <cb ed="#L" n="a"/> At the tabernacle in Silo, and in the city of Jerusalem, there was a
          school that surpassed all others that people now call a university. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e538">
          <ref><name>Samuel</name>’s Holy History</ref> notes that famous men had the government of
          those schools. We read in <ref>Kama</ref> that <name>Samuel</name>, the most intelligent,
          godly wise man was the governor and principal of Naioth, better known as Burse or the
          College of Prophets. <name>Helias</name> and <name>Heliseus</name> were the clearest
          lights of the Church of Israel. Both <name>Helias</name> and <name>Heliseus</name> were
          rulers over the schools of Hierico and Gilgal respectively. <name>Jeroboam</name>
          naughtily took down schools and treaded under foot beneath the order of the priests.
            <name>Jeroboam</name> manipulated people and places that were the refuse of their
          society. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e600">
          <name>Helias</name> and <name>Heliseus</name>, men of God, knew well that without schools,
          the doctrine could not flourish or be preserved. Therefore, both men applied themselves to
          the rejuvenation of schools. Wicked princes bestowed lawful tributes meant for the schools
          upon flatterers and bellies, better known as priests of the Tools of calves, and of Baal.
          By the goodness of the Lord, it came to pass that some good men bestowed tributes upon
          those who were desirous of learning, and who were content with a meager living, and who
          had valiant behavior during a corrupt age. Notable wise men and prophets who governed the
          schools were called fathers. The disciples and scholars who attended the schools were
          called sons of prophets. <name>Amos</name> and <name>Jeremiah</name> called the fathers
          and the sons 'parasites.' </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e656">
          <name>Amos</name> said, <quote>“I am no prophet…” <!--1114.xml-->
            <cb ed="#L" n="b"/> “neither am I the son of a prophet.”</quote>
          <name>Amos</name> was not, as far as we know, schooled in a liberal arts curriculum.
            <name>Amos</name> said again, <quote>“I have raised some of your sons as Prophets, and
            some of your young men as Nazarites.”</quote>
          <name>Jeremiah</name> commanded that these sons and young men received education from a
          Christian school. Later on, <name>Jeremiah</name> lamented and wailed in hope of his death
          during his captivity. Furthermore, the young men are called sons of the prophets because
          of the affection that they have for their school masters. The young scholars obey their
          school masters and revere them as if they had been their parents because they are grateful
          to study daily with them. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e719"> The princes were much more noble and wise. They diligently
          restored schools, and indirectly, they repaired ecclesiastical order. <name>David</name>,
            <name>Solomon</name>, <name>Jolaphat</name>, <name>Ezechias</name>, and
            <name>Josias</name> were the happiest and most virtuous princes because of their
          dedication to restoring Christian schools. During and after the captivity of Babylon, the
          Lord’s people scattered into many different kingdoms. But wherever they went, the created
          schools or synagogues. When the city of Jerusalem was restored, the Lord’s people returned
          and built schools and synagogues. The <ref>Acts of the Apostles</ref> mention that when
            <name>Saint Paul</name> preached the word of God among the Gentiles, he also went into
          the synagogues to teach. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e788">
          <name>Saint James the Apostle</name> said, “<name>Moses</name> would, in old times in
          every city that had him, preach in the synagogues.”<quote/>
          <name>Moses</name> did not speak about the cities of Judea and Galilee, but about the
          cities of the Gentiles in Syria, Cilicia, and Asia. What we read in the <ref>Acts of the
            Apostles</ref> shows that… <!--1115.xml-->
          <!-- 1085 -->
          <pb ed="#L" n="1115-"/>
          <cb ed="#L" n="a"/> the Lord’s people were dispersed and scattered abroad, but they did
          sometimes come to the holy city of Jerusalem. The <ref>Acts of the Apostles</ref> says,
            <quote>“There were dwelling at Jerusalem certain Jews, religious men, of all nations
            that are under heaven.”</quote>
          <name>Saint Paul</name> is confirmation of the passage in the <ref>Acts</ref>. He confirms
          that he was born free in the city of Tharsus and he traveled to Jerusalem to hear
          instruction at <name>Gamaliel</name>’s feet. <name>Saint Paul</name> wished to be a
          scholar under <name>Gamaliel</name>. We read in the <ref>Acts</ref> that in Jerusalem,
          there were colleges or Synagogues established by the Livertines, Cyrenians, Alerandrines,
          Cilicians, and Asians. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e863"> The use of schools continued until Christ’s time and after
          his ascension into heaven, almost until the destruction of the city. In the meantime, it
          may appear that the use of schools has been distinctly depraved during precise parts of
          history. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e880"> Christ, the son of God, our king and high bishop himself
          instituted the most famous school of all others. Christ called the twelve Apostles and the
          seventy disciples “chosen men.” The Apostles themselves drew many disciples. <name>Saint
            Paul</name> was the chosen instrument of God who converted the Gentiles. <name>Saint
            Paul</name> had many scholars in his company. A brief list of some of the men he
          associated with includes <name>Sopater of Berrhee</name>, <name>Luke of Antioch</name>,
            <name>Marke of Jerusalem</name>, <name>Barnabas</name>, <name>Eylua or Sylvanus</name>,
            <name>Caius</name> and <name>Timothie</name>, <name>Aristarchus</name>,
            <name>Secundus</name>, <name>Tychicus</name>, <name>Prophimus</name>,
          <name>Fitus</name>, <name>Linus</name>, <name>Erscens</name>, <name>Epaphras</name>,
            <name>Archippus</name>, <name>Philemon</name>, <name>Epaphroditus</name>, and
            <name>Artemas</name> among others. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e988">
          <name>Saint Paul</name> diligently taught good men who were studious, and ministers of the
          churches. He exhorted all men to be free from prejudice, and liberal minded in hopes that
          they should want nothing except God. Writing to…. <!--1115.xml-->
          <cb ed="#L" n="b"/>
          <quote><name>Titus</name>,</quote>
          <name>Saint Paul</name> says, <quote>"bring diligently <name>Zenas the Lawyer</name>, and
              <name>Apollo</name> to the belief that they may want nothing."</quote>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e1023"> In the <ref>thirteenth chapter of the Acts</ref> is the
          name of a famous and apostolic school at Antioch in Syria. <name>Eusebius of
            Cesarea</name> witnessed the noble schools in Alexandria, Egypt and in other renowned
          churches. We have declared the same in a larger fashion in the book that we have written
          about the institution of Bishops. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e1062"> In the process of time when all things pertaining to the
          church began to decline, ecclesiastical schools degenerated and became abbeys or colleges
          of canons and monks. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e1078"> Out of all the things we have discussed, I think that it
          is unknown to all men that schools do principally intend to preserve the church, and to
          maintain the holy ministry. In schools, art is a potentially profitable discipline because
          it can further the study of the holy scriptures which are the most important of all
          studies and knowledge. The knowledge of holy tongues, logic, natural philosophy, and
          mathematics are moderately known, and can be directed to the certain end of Godliness. Men
          may find a community of scholars who are diversely educated in various arts and
          disciplines yet who have not learned about holy exercises and studies. Some wicked beings
          are glutted with prophane study and they would condemn… <!--1116.xml-->
          <!-- 1086 -->
          <pb ed="#L" n="1116-"/>
          <cb ed="#L" n="a"/> holy scriptures as barbarous. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e1141"> You may find some scholars so involved with the study of
          mathematics that they would more likely become engineers or construction workers rather
          than Church leaders. These men are so concerned with the study of Astronomy, and 'the
          Astronomer’s Heaven' that they forget the blessed heaven, which is the seat of the saints.
          Heaven holds all that anyone needs to be sufficiently happy, however some astronomers
          believe that the knowledge of the motion of the visible heaven, and the course of the
          stars is happiness enough. Those that meddle too much with philosophy, the trifles of
          logic, and the rules of rhetoric never attain any end, nor do they ever think to donate to
          the edification of the church. Often, these types of men become preoccupied with academic
          debate. They often become contentious, arrogant, and controlling. These types of scholars
          do not seem to be content with how others speak or act. Certain scholars are not content
          with the traditional status of beliefs unless they are suitably adjusted with their own
          beliefs. These scholars do not sway from what they believe is true, and it impacts their
          capacity to listen to and understand others. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e1214"> These types of men confuse and complicate traditional
          beliefs with senseless disputations with the sole purpose of engaging in debate. They
          arrogantly judge what other men say and do even if the others are good and tolerable.
          Sometimes, these certain scholars will snap at perfectly normal men, and frivolously
          object to their beliefs. This behavior does not make certain scholars philosophers, but
          more so vain babblers. <!--1116.xml-->
          <cb ed="#L" n="b"/> These men spit out the poison of debates, contentions, variances,
          antagonisms and divisions against the Church. <name>Saint Paul the Apostle</name> spoke
          against this behavior to <name>Timothy</name>. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e1261">
          <name>Saint Paul</name> said, <quote>“This teach and exhort. Whoever teaches otherwise and
            doesn’t hold himself contented with the plentiful word of our Lord Jesus Christ and the
            doctrine according to godliness, is arrogant and ignorant. He who teaches as such wastes
            his time questioning and antagonizing with other men verbally. As a result, hatred,
            strife, slander, evil, suspicion, and vain conflict arise. These men become corrupt of
            heart and destitute of the truth, which is the only way to gain godliness. Avoid the
            company of such men.”</quote>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e1303"> Truly it never went well with the church when learned and
          studious men renounced the plain and pure nature of the word of God. These men turned
          their eyes another way, and not look at the word of God alone. In ancient times, certain
          scholars did not condemn the word of God, but they did attribute more of the word to
          traditions for the sake of convenience. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e1327"> However, this created errors and confirmed already
          presumed abuses of the church. After years have passed and gone, <name>Gratian</name> and
            <name>Lombard</name> along with other ecclesiastical writers decided to make an
          agreement of opinions and to gather together a perfect and certain sum explanation of
          divinity. By doing this, they did not only carry schools away from the scriptures, but
          they also intruded upon the doctrines of the church. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e1361"> After <name>Gratian</name> and <name>Lombard</name>,
            <name>Alexander</name>, <name>Albertus</name>, and <name>Thomas</name> decided not only
          to depend on those sentences. <!--1117.xml-->
          <!-- 1087 -->
          <pb ed="#L" n="1117"/>
          <cb ed="#L" n="a"/>
          <name>Alexander</name>, <name>Albertus</name> and <name>Thomas</name> tried to mingle
          philosophy with divinity and to reconcile them with each other to create one body. After
          decades of behavior like this, it came to pass that we had so many different sects, so
          many puddles crawling full of frogs, so many abbeys, and so many sophisters. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e1405"> If today we continue unhappily to couple philosophy with
          the holy scriptures and to superstitiously dispute and examine them by human rules or in
          the context of art, then we will corrupt the scriptures in schools. By corrupting the
          integrity of the scriptures in schools, we will have perverted the apostolic doctrine to
          the great detriment of the church. In the meantime, it is certain that art and learning
          can impact perspective and plainness in a positive manner when it is moderately and
          religiously applied with good judgement. The purpose of having such judgement will allow
          the scriptures to hold authority, and all other arts to obey laws and beliefs set by the
          scriptures. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e1445"> Let pure godliness be taught in ecclesiastical schools.
          Let godliness be the end of all our studies. Firstly, students should be diligently taught
          the catechism, and do not let them rest until they have learned it perfectly and made it
          familiar. Let the young growing godliness be increased daily with lectures and holy
          sermons. Let writings from the holy evangelists and apostles be read to the scholars so
          that the students may learn them perfectly. Let them comfortably learn the tongues and the
          good arts, and let them participate in writing and reasoning exercises. Let godliness be
          the end of all our studies. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e1487"> Above all, let godly Christian schools banish negligence
          and recklessness. <!--1117.xml-->
          <cb ed="#L" n="b"/> Let discipline, albeit occasionally harsh, flourish. If youth are
          corrupted in school and they are raised in that corruption, I pray, what shall we look for
          in their hands when they have authority over the church? Do not let us believe that they
          will be the salt of the church if they lack discipline and are crude and obtuse to the
          point where they will not abide by sharpness from one another. Should we think that they
          will become lights of the church if they themselves hate the light and are delighted in
          darkness and in the works of darkness? The sons of <name>Helie</name> were part of the
          church of Israel. The same were and continue to be the corrupt sons of the prophets in the
          church of Christ. Therefore, they will likely perish with the people who are under their
          care. Currently, it is offensive for schools to be too lenient. Mischief will never get
          washed away. A man could come into the school where he might initially see soldiers and
          ruffians, not those who should be scholars and students (who they commonly call clerks). </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e1569"> Fare, apparel, manners, words, nor do their deeds declare
          them to be of good disposition, honest or studious. I know that much can be ascribed to
          the unhappy and disjointed present. During this time, the stubborn and rebellious will not
          listen to the council of the elders. I know that there are serious offences committed
          through negligence. Fond gentleness is a negligent behavior to students in this authority. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e1600"> Regarding the welfare of the church, schools should be
          well… <!--1118.xml-->
          <!-- 1088 -->
          <pb ed="#L" n="1118-"/>
          <cb ed="#L" n="a"/> ordered. We must be diligent to prevent any offenses against God
          through our carelessness or negligence. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e1622"> I have said this already in regard to ecclesiastical
          schools, but here I discuss the topic as briefly as possible. In my more detailed book
          about the institution of the church and of bishops, I delve into this further. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e1638"> To maintain God’s ministry, schools, holy buildings, and
          ecclesiastical charges do require some good wealth and ability to correspond the matters. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e1655"> Thus, this discussion urges us to talk about
          ecclesiastical goods. God created a commonwealth in which he provided everything
          necessary. There are appointed standing fees paid to the holy ministry from the common
          parishioners who are of sound mind, called tithes such as grants or favors, in
          fruits, or in other kinds of offerings. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e1679">
          <name>Moses</name> expressed these requirements that God has for human beings in many
          words to clarify that man should fear the greed, desire, and covetousness of men. God
          commanded that these things be declared plainly and faithfully to the people. The law of
          nature commands that he who takes pain will be rewarded. To maintain common charges,
          there must be a common contribution. Tributes or revenues publicly gathered were not for
          any reason except public use. Part of the collected funds were given to the ministers for
          their ministry, part was disbursed to public buildings and holy charities, and part was
          employed to… <!--1118.xml-->
          <cb ed="#L" n="b"/> the relief of the poor. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e1735"> Although according to the <ref>new testament</ref>, the
          Levitical law claims that the priesthood would be eradicated, it is certain that the same
          universal law that commands its parishioners to pay public charges, should in turn be
          levied by public contributions. It is important not to abolish this law. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e1753"> We read that our Lord Jesus Christ lived on less than a
          tenth of the revenue of the current priests. Jesus lived on contributions of the godly. He
          executed a public function. He sent his disciples abroad to preach and he said, <quote>“Do not
          concern yourselves with food and clothing, because the laborer is worthy of his hire.”</quote> </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e1780"> In the primitive church, the apostles gathered to Christ
          and gave him their houses, lands, and money in order to preserve the ministry and other
          necessary things for the church. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e1819"> God appointed men, not angels to be ministers of the
          church, and he recommended that poor men <quote>“unto the church to stande in his stead.”</quote> </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e1830"> Men go through the motions of the holy ghost together in
          order to gather together, bestow money, houses, lands and other goods to the poor. The
          holy ministry must be maintained. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e1850"> It is evident that… <!--1119.xml-->
          <!-- 1089 -->
          <pb ed="#L" n="1119"/>
          <cb ed="#L" n="a"/> since the time of Christ and the Apostles in the church of the new
          testament, goods and possessions have been publicly gathered and received. These goods are
          bestowed upon those in need for public and common commodity (?). </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e1876"> <name>Gregorie, the first bishop of Rome</name> said that it was the
          custom in his time and the time before him that regarding finances, there should be four
          parts of the church of God. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e1891"> The first portion should go to the bishop and his family,
          the second for the clergy, the third for the poor and the fourth for repairing churches. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e1902"> However, there are many people that say that a bishop
          should not receive wages from the church. We will examine what Christ and his Apostles
          teach us about the matter. Christ our Lord never committed any unjust actions. As it is in
          the Bible, <quote>“maintenance from such women as he taught,
          who ministered unto him of their substance.”</quote> Jesus sent his disciples abroad and
          willed them not to concern themselves about food, water or clothing. Jesus said, <quote>“the
          laborer is worthy of his hire.”</quote> </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e1939"> The Lord judges that it is necessary to minister to the
          preachers’ needs. As long as preachers do no unworthy deed with their wages, they should
          be able to provide for themselves and their families. Jesus compared preachers not to idle
          men who eat freely of other men’s bread, nor to beggars, but to laborers. As our Lord sets
          down in law, it is a great offense to deny laborers their hire. <quote>“Even so their offense is
          not small ye suffer such as are faithful feeders of the flock, to perish and decay through
          need.”</quote> It is offensive if faithful feeders of the flock
          perish and decay through need. In another place in the Bible, the Lord says to his
          disciples… <!--1119.xml-->
          <cb ed="#L" n="b"/> <quote>“You have freely received, therefore give it freely.”</quote> Jesus spoke of
          the gift of working miracles and the benefit of health for the sick, diseased, and
          oppressed. It is written, <quote>“Heal the sick, cleanse the leprous, raise the dead, cast out
          devils.”</quote> He added to those words when he said, <quote>“You have received freely,
          therefore bestow freely.”</quote> Though the Apostles received rewards from the people to whom
          they preached, no man read that they took anything for the gift of healing that they had
          received in the Lord’s name. Like as <name>Heliseus</name> wouldn’t take
          anything at all even though it was freely offered by <name>Naaman the Syrian captain</name> who
          <name>Heliseius</name> cured of leprosy. The same <name>Heliseus</name> did not refuse the gift of the man that came
          to him from <name>Baalsalisa</name>. From <ref>the same Gospel of Christ our Lord</ref>, ministers have to learn
          how to use their wages from the church. The Lord commanded <name>Judas</name> to depart after seeing
          what was in his purse (silver coins). The disciples thought that he had been commanded to
          go and buy necessities that would serve for the holy day or for the poor. It is clear that
          the Lord used the stipend that he received to provide necessities for himself and his
          family, and also to give alms thereof. In sum, make note that the ministers of the church
          should provide necessary things for their living, function and the maintenance of their
          household from the wages they receive from the church. Again, they may also use the same
          wages to give alms to the poor because the wages were earned truthfully by the ministers.
          The Lord said clearly in the law that the tithes… <!--1120.xml-->
          <!-- 1090 -->
          <pb ed="#L" n="1120"/>
          <cb ed="#L" n="a"/> Oblations or holy revenues like from the Levites are all acceptable to
          him because they sacrificed anything that they could offer from their own chest, store
          or possessions. If a laborer offers to God anything of his hire or wages, meaning if he
          gives to the poor, doesn’t it seem like an acceptable sacrifice to God? Therefore, it is
          very acceptable that the minister bestows alms from the wages of the holy ministry.
          Another example is about a laborer who is building a church. This laborer receives wages
          from the church. Should a man say that the laborer took alms and his alms should not be
          given out to others? No because he received wages for his work because he did labor.
          Therefore, he gives alms of his own wages, and of his own lawful and proper goods.
          Therefore, it is clear that the minister of the church does not live by alms. He should
          not give alms from alms he received, but he did labor for his wages and therefore he
          received the reward of his work as a laborer does. The Lord himself compared the minister
          to the laborer, so it is right that a minister should earn wages as a laborer does. If any
          man is too dishonest to listen to me, he will not hear what I say. Instead, he should hear
          what <name>Paul the Apostle</name> says. <quote>“If we sow spiritual things, is it a great matter if we mow
          your carnal things?”</quote> And again, <quote>“The elders that govern well are worthy of double honor,
          especially those that travel in preaching and teaching.”</quote> The Scripture says, <quote>“You shall
          not muzzle the mouth of the oxe treading through the corn.”</quote> And, <quote>“The laborer is worthy of
          his hire.”</quote> Therefore, <name>the Apostle</name> does not think that inestimable goodness of the ministry
          can by any means be recompensed with a vile thing, meaning earthly wages. Again, <name>Paul</name>
          says, <quote>“They that labor, not they that loiter in teaching”</quote> <!--1120.xml-->
          <pb ed="#L" n="1120"/>
          <cb ed="#L" n="b"/> <name>Paul</name> compares these men that labor to an ore that is a toiling beast,
          and a thresher out of corn, and also to a laboring man. I do warn you that because
          in our wicked and thankless world, certain men—monsters—most unthankful that believe that
          ministers do nothing at all, even the most faithful that do their duty. These monsters cry
          out and claim that ministers eat as beggars, and that it cost them nothing. By name and
          infamy these monsters are terrifying because they forsake the study of good learning and
          divinity. They abhor the ministry, as though it is beggarly and dishonest. In such groups
          of men, the devil grows his kingdom through abuse, appropriately using to his benefit our
          ingratitude and malice. Why do these men not suffer themselves to be among Christ and the
          Holy Apostles, who were fed and maintained by the churches stipend, then to be judged as
          thankless and proud people that scrape and gather all their goods together by usury and
          wicked means. Or at least if they had not gotten their goods by sinister means, they
          probably received them through liberality and the goodness of God, for which they never
          sweat or worked for. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e2321"> <name>Saint Paul</name> proved many arguments that ministers have a
          right to receive a stipend for the holy ministry. He said, <quote>“Have we not power and
          authority to eat and drink, or may we not bring with us a woman or sister?”</quote> For <name>Paul</name> meant
          the lawfulness and authority to receive anything necessary for himself, his wife and his
          whole household. And for that… <!--1121.xml-->
          <!-- 1091 -->
          <pb ed="#L" n="1121"/>
          <cb ed="#L" n="a"/> He asked a question, he showed what he meant, and therefore he
          declared a plain truth of equity among all men. He added examples, not of every man
          personally, but of all generally, especially the Apostles of Christ and those that were
          kin of Christ by blood saying: <quote>“Even as the other Apostles and brothers of our Lord and
          <name>Cephas</name>?”</quote> And who is <name>Cephas</name>, but <name>Peter</name>? To this, <name>Cephas</name> the Lord said in the <ref>first chapter
          out of <name>Saint John</name></ref>, <quote>“You shall be called <name>Cephas</name>, which if a man interprets it, means a
          stone. But <name>Peter</name> was surnamed of a rock to the intent the interpretation of the name may
          always be the same.”</quote> </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e2423"> Who, I pray to you, are the Lords brethren but <name>John</name> and
          <name>James</name>, and <name>James the brother of Judas</name>, and <name>Judas</name> and <name>Simon the brethren of James</name>. <quote>“All
          these,”</quote> said <name>Saint Paul</name>, <quote>“lived off the stipend they had, that was gathered from the
          common assembly of the Church.”</quote> Besides these examples, <name>Paul</name> added others like them that
          are commonly put into practice. He said, <quote>“Who goes to war at his own cost and charges? Who
          plants a vineyard and doesn’t eat of the fruit from it? Who feeds a flock and does not
          drink their milk?”</quote> <name>Paul</name> brings forth these similitudes and properly applies them. The
          ministers of the church are sometimes called soldiers or vineyard keepers, or husbandmen
          or shepherds. Who, I pray, is so far from reason that he would deny meat and clothing to
          soldiers, husbandmen and shepherds? They take pains in warfare, husbandry, and with
          cattle. <!--1121.xml-->
          <cb ed="#L" n="b"/> The true hearted men are indifferent. They acknowledge that the
          ministers of the Church may live by the ecclesiastical ministry. Very few men object that
          these humane parables and similitudes taken from common use prove nothing in an
          ecclesiastical cause. He added, “<quote>Do I speak these things according to man? Doesn’t the law
          say the same? It is written in the law of <name>Moses</name>, you shall not muzzle the ox that treads
          out the corn.”</quote> “<quote>As though he should say, I have in a readiness for the confirmation of
          our right, not only human similitudes but also testimonies of the holy scripture”</quote> As <name>Paul</name>
          would say, I have readily confirmed our [ministers’] right to wages, not only through
          human comparisons, but also by citing testimonies in the holy scriptures. <name>Saint Paul</name>, in
          <ref>chapter 2 of Deuteronomy</ref> discusses how to nourish laboring oxen. If any man says that the
          other passages should not be used in comparison to preachers but only referring to oxen,
          he should then look at this passage. <name>Paul</name> says, <quote>“Does God care for oxen? Or does he not
          speak altogether for our sake? It is doubtless that God has written it for our sake, that
          he who plows can plow in hope, and that he who harvests in hope may be the
          partaker of his hope.”</quote> The Lord said in his law that he would provide for us. For he
          equally gathered, by a certain syllogism or argument his proofs for the debate. If the
          lord provided for beasts and cattle, and considered them, how much more for men would he
          provide? It is an unjust thing that a husbandman could labor without his ox and without
          hope, meaning in vain, and without commodity. Therefore, since it is an unjust thing, for
          the minister to exercise ecclesiastical harvesting <!--1122.xml-->
          <!-- 1092 -->
          <pb ed="#L" n="1122-"/>
          <cb ed="#L" n="a"/> in the church without hope or due payment.
          Moreover, <name>the Apostle</name>
          rejects the possibility that the spiritual ministry does not receive any corporal reward
          and is only allowed to reap spiritual rewards. He answered, <quote>“If we sow unto you spiritual
          things, is it important that we reap your temporal things?”</quote> <name>The Apostle</name> thinks that the
          Corinthians gave nothing when they gave temporal things when these temporal goods are
          compared with eternal good things, which the ministers provide in their teachings. Look at
          how far the soul excels the body. One can accomplish much more with spiritual goods rather
          than temporal goods. <name>The Apostle</name> concealed an argument in his discussion where he
          admonished that farmers who sow should also reap. In this issue there are great
          inequalities because the ministers sow better spiritual rewards, but do not receive nearly
          as much payment as other laborers. Some men think that ministers do not do anything,
          however this is untrue because they set light by God and carry forth the divine
          ministry. <name>Saint Paul</name> confirmed his own right through an example with others when he said,
          <quote>“If other people partake in the power towards you, why should we not?”</quote> Seeing nothing took
          more pains among the Corinthians than <name>Saint Paul</name>. No man was more worthy of reward
          compared to the ministers. <name>Saint Paul</name> confirmed his right to a wage by example of the
          Lord’s commandment and ordinance that said: <quote>“You do not know what pains the ministers take
          in holy things, what they do eat of the holy things and that they the ministers of the
          altar are partakers of the altar?"</quote> So far as the Lord ordained, that those people who
          preach the Gospel should live off the Gospel. Where does the Lord ordain this? He ordains
          this in the <ref>Gospel</ref> when he says, <quote>“the laborer is worthy of his hire.”</quote> I judge this… <!--1122.xml-->
          <cb ed="#L" n="b"/>
          to be observed while the <name>Apostle</name> spoke in plain
          words, that the Lord instituted his ordinance concerning the maintenance of the ministers
          of the Church in order to imitate the laws of the ancient Jewish peoples. Here we should
          understand that in cases like this, we should not reject the ancient institutions of our
          fathers. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e2783"> <name>Saint Paul the Apostle</name> did not use his authority as he
          could have, but this means nothing regarding these things because these practices are
          questions of deed and of what is right. Indeed he took nothing of the Corinthians for
          difference causes, but he did take from other churches. He did not receive anything from
          the Church of Thessalonica. All that he did is not prejudicial to the equity of the right
          of each church. <name>Saint Paul</name> said to the Corinthians, <quote>“I have robbed other churches because
          I have received wages from them, however, I did this with the intent that I might do you
          service. When I was with you and I was wanted, I was not burdensome to any man. The things
          that I lacked were given to me by brethren from Macedonia.”</quote> To the Thessalonians he said,
          <quote>“We haven’t behaved like ourselves inordinately among you, neither did we take bread for
          nothing. With labor and pain both night and day, doing our work, we intended that we would
          not be a burden to any of you. Not that it is lawful for us to do that, but because we set
          ourselves down as role models, we do deserve bread.”</quote> <name>Saint
          Paul</name> then said to the Thessalonians, <quote>“I ask that you acknowledge the people who labor
          among you and who are over you in the Lord, who admonish you…”</quote> <!--1123.xml-->
          <!-- 1093.xml-->
          <pb ed="#L" n="1123"/>
          <cb ed="#L" n="a"/> <quote>“So that you take them in singular love through love for their work’s
          sake. Be at peace with them”</quote> Let as much as is necessary be given to Church ministers and
          teachers so far as what is given is honest and necessary. Thus, this is what is spoken
          about the due proportion that is to be paid to pastors. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e2913"> In the past, the second part of ecclesiastical goods were
          allotted to clerks. Clerks are the harvest of pastors, studiers of divinity, and are
          completely disposed to the holy ministry. As long as these clerks have dedicated
          themselves and all that they have completely to the Church and the ministry, it is fit
          that they should be nourished and maintained by the costs of the Church. It is convenient
          that they are nourished meanly because they should be an example of people who live
          inexpensively. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e2946"> To be brought up wealthily does not
          agree with the ministries of the church. Therefore, <name>Amos</name> found fault that the Nazarites
          drank wine because he believed that drunkards did not maintain the church but instead
          destroy it. We spoke of this matter in another place. In sum, it is appropriate that due
          portions be paid to priests, schoolmasters, scholars and all other ecclesiastical
          workers/persons. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e2979"> The third part of ecclesiastical goods are appointed for
          the poor. There are different types of poor people; widows, pupils, orphans and infants
          who are cast out and who’s parents are unknown. Some of the poor people are worn with old
          age and spent with diseases. There are infinite kinds of diseases, but the most grievous
          are these that follow: leprosy, fury, madness, the French pocks, scabby of India or… <!--1123.xml-->
          <!-- 1093.xml-->
          <cb ed="#L" n="b"/> Naples, palsy, gout, and many more. There are some poor men with land,
          and there are also some strangers that are banished from their country and home for the
          sake of righteousness, and because of the word of God. There are some people who have yet
          to overcome extreme poverty and are in grave danger of falling into it. If these people
          are not helped with ready money, they will come to be kept by the church box. There are
          some poor people who are prisoners of war, or by land like waters and fires among other
          mishaps that prevent them from returning home. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e3046"> Of all the people’s health that the Lord protects, the
          Lord tells us to be mindful. He says, <quote>“Whatever we bestow upon the poor, we bestow upon
          Him (the Lord).”</quote> If we despise and do not regard the poor, without a doubt we despise and
          neglect our Lord God himself. Out of duty, we should help the poor out of our own good
          will through offering counsel, comfort, medicines, cures, money, meat, drink, clothes,
          lodging and assistance by any means else that we can manage in all such matters and cases
          if they should need our help. The Church’s goodness is not sufficient to give ample aid to
          the poor in full. Let the abundance of good faithful people supply their want. However, if
          there is a sufficient amount of goods laid up in storage, let these goods contribute to
          the liberality of the godly. This is often taken away by governors through negligence or
          wickedness and it causes the necessity of the poor to be ignored and unfulfilled. In that
          case, the tempests of infelicity are poured forth upon the common wealths… <!--1124.xml-->
          <!-- 1094.xml -->
          <pb ed="#L" n="1124"/>
          <cb ed="#L" n="a"/> and kingdoms. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e3120"> People who do not give part of their private goods to the
          poor when they are able will be sharply punished. They who do not donate will be plagued
          with grievous calamities. Those that wickedly, sacrilegiously and forcibly steal from
          riches given for the common use of the poor will face even more grievous calamities. The
          man that has riches in this world and sees his brother in need, and who then denies him
          affection, and who is cruel to him, therefore is taking from the poor that which is
          already given. The man who takes from the poor what is already given is committing
          sacrilege. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e3157"> In the Bible, the Sodomites along with fellow cities were
          burned and destroyed because they did not strengthen the hand of the poor, but rather
          weakened it. The Moabits and Chanaanites were destroyed for their disdain of
          strangers and for avoiding the poor. You may wonder why we use examples from so far in the
          past. Why don’t we discuss the last sentence of the high Judge who sits in his heavenly
          judgement seat established in the clouds? He said, <quote>“Come everyone, blessed of my father,
          possess the kingdom that was prepared for you from the beginning of the world. I have been
          hungry, and you have given me meat. I have been thirsty, and you have given me drink. I
          was a stranger and you harbored me, I was naked, and you clothed me. I was sick and you
          visited me, I was in prison, and you came to me.”</quote> The Evangelist also added a statement
          that agrees with the purpose of this sermon: <quote>“The just will answer and say, Lord, when we
          saw you hungry and gave you meat, saw you thirsty and gave you drink? Saw you homeless and
          lodged you, or naked… <!--1124.xml-->
          <!-- 1094.xml-->
          <cb ed="#L" n="b"/> clothed you? Or when we saw you sick or in prison and came to you?"</quote> The
          king will answer them, <quote>"Verily I say to you, in that you did unto the least of my brethren
          you did unto me. Then shall he say also to them that are on his left hand, Depart from me
          you cursed people, into everlasting fire that is prepared for the devil and his angels. I
          was hungry and you gave me no meat, I was thirsty and you gave me no drink, I was a
          stranger and you did not harbor me, I was naked and you didn’t clothe me. I was sick and
          in prison and you did not visit me."</quote> Then they will answer and say to Him, <quote>“Lord when did
          we see you hungry, thirsty or a stranger? Naked, or sick or in prison and when did we not
          minister to you?"</quote> Then the Lord will answer them, saying, <quote>"Verily I say to you, in as much
          as you did it not unto one of the least of these people, you did to me.”</quote> It follows after,
          <quote>“These people will go to everlasting punishment but the righteous into everlasting life.”</quote>
          The Lord in another place in the <ref>Gospel</ref> substitution the poor in his stead said, <quote>“You have
          the poor with you always, and when you will you may do them good, but me you won’t have
          always.”</quote> Therefore we read that the primitive church was careful in providing for the
          poor, even to the working of miracles. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e3315"> <name>Saint Paul</name> in all places commanded the poor to the church
          of God. He made collections for the poor in almost every church. He also gathered
          blessings and distributed them with great judgement, faith and diligence. As it appears in
          almost all of his epistles but specifically in the <ref>15th to the Romans</ref>, in <ref>the first to the
          Corinthians</ref>, <ref>the sixteenth chapter in the second epistle to… <!--1125.xml-->
          <!-- 1095.xml -->
          <pb ed="#L" n="1125"/>
          <cb ed="#L" n="a"/> the Corinthians</ref> and <ref>the eighth and ninth chapters</ref>, and to <ref>the
          Galathians</ref>. <name>Saint Paul</name> says, <quote>“While we have time, let us do good towards all men,
          especially towards the household of faith.”</quote> In the <ref>first Epistle to <name>Timothie</name></ref>, he warned
          that there should be consideration who should receive help and who should not receive
          help. In the same epistle, he gave charge to <name>Timothie</name> and to all the bishops and taught
          them how to deal with the richer sort in the Church. He said, <quote>“Command the rich in this
          world not to be high minded. Neither should they put their trust in uncertain riches, but
          in the living God who gives us all things abundantly to enjoy. God intends that the rich
          and all things do good, that they may be rich in good works, that they be ready to give
          and bestow willingly. The rich should lay a good foundation against the time to come so
          they can take hold of life everlasting.”</quote> He said to the Hebrews, <quote>“To do good and to
          distribute forget not: with such sacrifice God is pleased.”</quote> </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e3430"> Riches were gathered even in the time of the Apostles to
          assist the necessity of the poor. Deacons were appointed by the church as providers and
          stewards. Among those first Deacons were the most famous, of whom the <ref>Acts of the Apostles</ref>
          make mention, and also the notable <name>martyr of Christ Laurence</name>. The writings of the ancient
          fathers testify that with those ecclesiastical goods, prisoners were redeemed out of
          captivity, poor m aids of lawful years were married, hospitals, almeries (places where
          alms were given), spittles (place for the diseased), and nurseries were built to entertain
          poor travelers, for the maintenance of the poor that were born in that country, for the
          relief of the sick and diseased, for the necessity of old men, and… <!--1125.xml-->
          <!-- 1095.xml -->
          <cb ed="#L" n="b"/> for the honest bringing up of pupils and orphans. Concerning these
          matters there are still existent certain imperial laws. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e3496"> In reforming our churches, we must take very diligent heed that there 
          be no offense committed on this behalf through oversight or of purpose.
          We must make sure that the poor are not defrauded and that by taking away some abuses,
          we do not bring in anymore. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e3514"> If there are plenty of goods, let the poor keep them. If
          there are none, let the Church gather them from the rich. Then let the state of the poor
          be searched so that the poor’s necessities and provisions are taken care of. Once people
          know what the poor have and do not have, let their needs be met speedily, gently and
          diligently. If any of the common goods remain, keep them to ensure against calamities that
          may ensue in the future. Let nothing be consumed unprofitably or ungodly. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e3545"> Again, do not let the treasure of the poor get taken from
          them by fraud, and cause an increase of their poverty. There may be similar offenses
          committed on both sides. For on each side the poor are defrauded of their goods. We have
          intreated in another place in these Decades about liberality, and about providing for the
          poor in other works. <name>Lewis Viues</name> wrote a very good work about relieving the poor. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e3577"> The fourth and last part of the goods of the church
          pertains to holy buildings like churches, schools, and houses belonging to churches and
          schools. Churches that gather companies together are also called congregations and are the
          houses of the Lord our God. Not that God who the wide compass of the heavens cannot
          comprehend… <!--1126.xml-->
          <!--1196.xml-->
          <pb ed="#L" n="1126"/>
          <cb ed="#L" n="a"/> would dwell in houses of that nature, but because the congregation and
          people of God meet together in these houses to worship, and to perform due honor to God.
          To hear the word of God, to receive the Lord’s sacraments, and to pray for the assistance
          and presence of God. Thus, churches are necessary for the institution of the church and
          for the people of God. I have said in the disputations of prayer, that churches are
          touching places for holy assemblies. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e3634"> At the commandment of God, <name>Moses</name> built a movable church,
          and afterward the <name>wise king Solomon</name> founded a standing church at great cost. We must know
          that after God had sent Christ and fulfilled the figures, he would not like such great
          charges. Before God made the law, the patriarchs did not ever build
          ministries and great churches. Even after the disannulling of the law in the church of
          Christ, it is known that sparing cleanliness pleases God the most. God dislikes foolish
          buildings, like the unwise building of Babylon. These people tried to build the top of the
          tower above the clouds. God does not like the righteousness of Churches, especially when
          they try to gather his church together from all parts of the world. God does not like this
          because he teaches simplicity and contempt of the rich. A church 
          is big enough as long as it is sufficient to receive everyone that belongs to it because
          the place is provided for men to inhabit, not for God. Above all things, let that place be
          clean and holy. A church is hallowed or consecrated in an unsuperstitious manner. Not with
          the rehearing of certain words, or the practice of certain marking <!--1126.xml-->
          <!-- 1096.xml -->
          <cb ed="#L" n="b"/> signs and characters, not with oil or purging fire, but because of
          God’s will and his commandment. God’s commandment bids us to assemble and to come
          together, and it promises his presence among us. God is present when there is holy use of
          the church. In the temple, the holy church of God gathers together, and the people declare
          the most blessed word of God. The holy sacraments of God are received in the temple, and
          acceptable prayers are poured forth to Him. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e3750"> To clarify, the location of the church is nothing holy,
          but because holy things are done in that place, the place itself becomes holy. Therefore,
          all profanities and filthiness should be far from the holy temple of the Lord. The
          senators court or seat of judgement is said to be so holy a thing that whoever in word or
          deed acts irreverently towards it should be accused of treason. Yet in this court, the
          senators are the only people gathered and assembled together to hear matters of suitors in
          transitory business that will become irrelevant. How much more reverently should we treat
          our temples then, where the children of God come to worship him and hear the true word of
          God, and to receive his holy sacraments? Therefore, we must hate and abandon all
          superstition in temples so that we do not falsely love the profanation of them. We cannot
          abide by that. We do not have leisure at this time to consider how temples rehearse and
          search out superstitions. We have spoken about this in another place. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e3823">
          <!--1127.xml-->
          <!-- 1097.xml -->
          <pb ed="#L" n="1127"/>
          <cb ed="#L" n="a"/> Among the fathers of the old time, I find that there is a matter of
          controversy about what part of the world we should turn to when we pray. <name>Socrates the
          historiographer</name> wrote in the <ref>22nd chapter of his fifth book</ref> about the ancient apostolic
          church of the world at Antioch. It reads, <quote>“At Antioch in Syria, the Church is set contrary
          to itself and others because the altar does not look to the East, but it looks towards the
          West.”</quote> It is possible that they imitated the fashion of the old people in building and
          setting their tabernacle and fashioning their temple. They worshipped God by turning
          towards the west because of the coming of Christ at a later time and at the end of the
          world. Otherwise, it is common that men worship with their faces towards the East. In all
          these matters there should not be superstition, dissention, licentiousness and offense. In
          this respect, a man should pray how he wants. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e3895"> There should not be a temple built for worshipping
          saints. We should only build temples for God, to whom all honor and worship are due. We
          are taught this by examples of ancient fathers, and the determination of scripture.
          Heathen idolaters built temples to creatures and by doing this, they sinned against the
          true and eternal God by committing this grievous offense. In his book <ref>De civitate Dei</ref>,
          <name>Saint Augustine</name> says plainly, <quote>“We build not temples unto our martyrs.”</quote> And again in his
          <ref>first book against <name>Maximus, a bishop of Arians</name></ref>, <quote>“If we should build a church of timber and
          stones unto some excellent holy angel, should we not be cursed by the truth of Christ, and
          the church of god? Why would we do a service… <!--1127.xml-->
          <!-- 1097.xml -->
          <cb ed="#L" n="b"/> unto a creature that is due only to God? Therefore, if we commit
          sacrilege by making a temple to every creature whatsoever, how may it be that God is not
          true unto whom we make no temple, but we ourselves are a temple for him?”</quote> These people who
          build temples for creatures should be known as liars. Men have affirmed that temples were
          built by certain religious men in the worship of the apostles while they were alive. We
          have discussed this in times past, as we have also discussed the righteousness of the
          Church, and the unprofitable expenses thereof in the first book titled <ref>De origine erroris,
          in the 21st chapter</ref>. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e4007"> Instruments that belong to the church should be holy,
          clean and void of all riches, and far from any kind of superstition. The instruments of
          a church are a holy seat or pulpit where the minister may teach and preach, convenient
          seats for the congregation, a fount ready to baptize infants, and the Lord's table. On the
          Lord's table there are necessary things such as water, bread, wine, books, candles, baskets
          and cups. These things used to be made of gold, but good and godly bishops would often
          melt them to deliver prisoners out of captivity and feed people who were going to perish
          from hunger. I have gathered many examples of this in my book <ref>Of the Institution of
          Bishops in the 9th chapter</ref>. As for candles which we mention even now, it is sure that
          ancient fathers used them in the churches to drive away the darkness of night. We see this
          in the <ref>20th chapter of the Acts of the Apostles</ref>. However, it is a foolish matter, and not
          religious to use lights in the worship of God. <name>Lactantius</name> cried out <!--1128.xml-->
          <pb ed="#L" n="1128"/>
          <cb ed="#L" n="a"/> <quote>“Should we judge him to be lucid when he offers the light of a burning
          wax candle or taper for a present to the author and giver of light? He requires a
          different kind of light at our hands, one that is not smokey but clear and bright to
          encourage the light of the mind.”</quote> A man may commonly see that in these days a great
          part of worship to God is displayed in the offering of candles. This thing is clean
          against the manifest truth. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e4118"> Among other instruments of the Church, bells are common.
          At this time, bells are the equivalent of trumpets in the old time were for the people of
          God. Bells serve to call the congregation together, and they are also tokens and warnings.
          Bells are wonderfully superstitious. They are christened by bishops, and it is a
          common belief that they have power to stop any great tempest. In the old time, men were
          stirred to prayer by the ringing of the bells whenever a tempest began. Now, the ringing
          of the bells seems to have a peculiar kind of virtue because of their consecration. Who
          would not marvel and be astonished at this extreme blindness? Moreover, they used bells to
          announce the dead. All things that are superstitious should be condemned. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e4168"> The true use of church goods consists of what we
          discussed before. It follows naturally that the abuse of church goods therefore must occur
          in the rotaries, whether it is in one way or many ways. Justice and equity should be kept
          in these church goods as well in all other things. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e4188"> We should not take from one man and give to another, but
          we should give to everyone something that can be his own. <!--1128.xml-->
          <cb ed="#L" n="b"/> Therefore, we should not take anything from the poor and give it to
          the ministers of the church. Neither should we take the portion belonging to the ministers
          to provide for their necessities and give it to the poor. The holy scripture gives one
          portion of church goods to the ministers of the Church, and the same church implores us to
          give to the poor a portion for them. Thus, if the bishops or ministers of the church take
          all of the church goods for themselves and do not give to the poor their due parts, the
          ministers defile themselves with sacrilege. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e4235"> If the ministers do not take all of the goods of the
          church but do unjustly take more than they need to survive, or they take more than the
          decree of God and the Apostles allows, or they spend their portion in an unwise manner,
          they commit a grievous offense. They sin greatly, most horribly, if they waste the goods
          of the poor in hunting, gambling, drinking and rioting, whore hunting or warfare, while
          they have no regard for what is done for the church. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e4272"> If a just and good portion is provided to the poor,
          perhaps there is a fault in this point. In the Steward or Almonar through favor or hatred
          that they who need most will have nothing, and the least worthy has most, then in this
          case, there is also a great offense committed through filthy abuse. Of all abuses, that is
          the most shameful, which is currently most common. We bestow great costs and charges to
          stones and stocks, meaning upon idols void of all understanding, but there is no regard <!--1129.xml-->
          <!-- 1099.xml -->
          <pb ed="#L" n="1129"/>
          <cb ed="#L" n="a"/> for the poor who are the perfect images of God. This kind of madness
          is sacrilegious. Even though many others have already spoken at length about the abuse of
          the Church goods, we have also set down certain matters concerning the same abuses
          elsewhere. For now, I will not speak of this topic anymore </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e4333"> Now I would like to discuss holy time which is somewhat
          similar to the discussion we had about holy places. We have disputed these doctrines
          elsewhere, but we have also discussed these particular doctrines when expounding upon the
          ten commandments. The only note I will add at this present moment about holy time is that
          there should not be odious contention in the church concerning this matter, but that in
          this case and other cases like it, there must be discipline with charity. We must be
          mindful of contention about keeping Easter. With much danger and detriment, it has for a
          long time troubled the churches of the East and the West. Beware that in any case, through
          contention there is a gap open for Satan to enter. It is profitable in my
          opinion to remember the advice that <name>Saint Augustine</name> gave. He said, <quote>“That which has
          enjoined us and is neither against fair nor good manners is to be counted as indifferent
          and to be observed according to the society in which the people life.”</quote> In the <ref>188th
          epistle to <name>Januarius</name></ref>. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e4410"> Discipline and correction of ministers is a
          responsibility that belongs to the holy ministry as well. Our Lord Christ emphasizes how
          necessary this is in the following quote. He says, <quote>“You are the salt of the earth. If the
          salt loses her saltiness, how would we salt anything else? <!--1129.xml-->
          <!-- 1099.xml -->
          <cb ed="#L" n="b"/> It is not good for anything to be thrown out the doors and to be
          trampled underfoot of men.”</quote> I know that there are some men that boast that they have
          certain privileges which exempts them from all discipline. They are deceived because the
          Lord has made all ministers of his church subject to discipline. The people who would be
          exempted from this discipline are not Christ’s minsters, but he himself is free from
          discipline because the Lord has subjected and bound him to it. Against the commandment of God, 
          there is no Pope’s law, no privilege
          of kind or emperor of force. No man can abrogate the decree of the high God. The Lord
          commanded a warning to correct every brother that goes amiss. Therefore, the Lord would
          encourage us to sharply admonish the ministers of the churches that are negligent and who
          go astray. Truly, the Lord himself often sharply reproved the whole order of Priests of
          the church of Jerusalem. <name>Helie, the Lord’s priest</name>, is not discussed often in the holy
          scripture because he did not convince his sons to become Priests with sharper
          discipline. We read how the prophets of the Lord bitterly blamed the
          Colleges of Priests and the High Priests. There are examples in every place throughout
          holy history and in the writings of the prophets. <name>Saint Paul</name> reproved <name>the most holy
          Apostle Saint Peter</name> at Antioch in Syria in front of the whole congregation because he was
          not teaching directly according to the prescript rule of the Gospel. To be short, Christ
          called himself in the revelation which was made to <name>Saint John the Apostle</name>, and in the
          revelation Christ sharply admonished and reproved the Angels, that is to say <!--1130.xml-->
          <!-- 1100.xml -->
          <pb ed="#L" n="1130"/>
          <cb ed="#L" n="a"/>the ministers of the churches. <name>Saint Paul the Apostle</name> said, <quote>“Do not
          accuse elders unless there are two or three witnesses. The elders that do offend should be
          scolded in front of the entire congregation so that the other elders would be afraid to
          offend.”</quote> In the scriptures, there are notable examples of holy princes who, by their laws,
          have arrested high ministers of the churches and who have removed them from their
          positions and stripped them of their degrees because it was not enough to discharge them
          from their duties. It is a necessity that the good estate of the people of God requires
          that the offending ministers are deposed. It is better that the church makes an example of
          a few evil ministers than put the congregations’ lives in danger of body and soul. This is
          because the churches and congregations are destroyed through the negligence and
          ungodliness of wicked pastors. Let those pastors get deposed as quickly as possible. To
          ensure that the ministers of the churches are easily kept in their function and calling,
          the ancient fathers from the old church only held Convocations of the Clergy once or twice
          each year. By applying these restraints, they were able to prevent some evil ministers
          from joining the ministry. So that I do not discuss anything too far fetched here dearly
          beloved, I will recite what is read in the <ref>Imperial Constitutions</ref> by the <name>Emperor
          Justinian</name>. He commands his audience in this manner: <quote>“The ancient fathers solemnly held
          convocations for the clergy twice a year in every province so that everyone who is
          applying is examined and amended by competent correction. It seems now more than ever that
          this this correction is necessary to fix bad and unlawful behavior. <!-- 1130.xml -->
          <!-- 1100.xml-->
          <cb ed="#L" n="b"/> Because of such negligence, we have found so many ministers to be
          trapped in error and sin. Now, we command all provinces to hold a Synod in July or
          September at the place of the Patriarchs or the Bishops. At this synod, everyone can
          discuss matters of faith, canonical questions and the administration of ecclesiastical
          goods and services. Here, everyone can also discuss offenses against the church, or other
          matters that require correction. Given the former statements, we should note that the
          laity reaps a profit when citizens and leaders have true faith, an honest life, and face
          the amendment of themselves.”</quote> Immediately after he says, <quote>“Moreover, we command the
          lieutenants of the provinces to address these concerns. If they see that these needs are
          not being met, they should urge the Bishops to assemble synods. If the provinces believe
          that the Bishops are seeking delay in a negligent manner, they should proceed with due
          correction against wrongdoers.”</quote> This is all I will report from the Caesarian
          decree. Therefore, the bishops should take heed that there is nothing wrong with the
          clergy beneath them in position to take action against their negligence. If the bishops
          forget their duty, the magistrate should see their sluggishness that will inevitably cause
          the destruction of the whole church and all the ministers of Christ. It is easy for vices
          to continually influence ministers of Christ unless there is consistent admonition and
          correction in the Church. The things in the Church that we think are the firmest will fall
          to decay and perish sooner than we think unless we admonish vice and sin. The Lord would
          have the offending <!--1131.xml-->
          <!-- 1101.xml -->
          <pb ed="#L" n="1131"/>
          <cb ed="#L" n="a"/> ministers of the churches privately admonished and corrected in front
          of the whole church. The ancient church had a holy senate of elders that diligently warned
          the offenders and corrected them sharply. The senate of elders also excluded the offenders
          from ecclesiastical fellowship if they thought that there was no hope of amendment. In
          later years, the popes and bishops tyrannically took that kind of punishment into their
          own hands. They exercised this power sacrilegiously and contrary to the way the first
          institution used it. They turned a wholesome medicine into a hurtful poison. It became
          abominable to both the good and the bad. <name>Saint Paul</name> taught that this kind of punishment
          was permitted by the Lord to restrain the licentiousness of many people. He said, <quote>“I have
          decreed that he who committed this offense when you are gathered together in the name
          of our Lord Jesus Christ and my spirit is with you, together with the power of our Lord
          Jesus Christ, that you be delivered to Satan and to the destruction of the flesh that the
          spirit may have saved in the day of the Lord Jesus.”</quote> This is the power and revengement of
          the Elders of the church. The means is the destruction of the flesh. The end is the safety
          of the spirit, or the saving of a faithful man. The same <name>Apostle Paul</name> said to the
          Thessalonians, <quote>“If there is any man that does not obey our words, identify him to me in a
          letter and make sure that you do not associate with him. He should be ashamed. Do not
          count him as an enemy but warn him as a brother.”</quote> The <name>same Apostle</name> plainly showed in
          another place <!--1131.xml-->
          <!-- 1101.xml -->
          <cb ed="#L" n="b"/> Who should be punished by the ecclesiastical sword. This does not mean
          offenders though weakness of the flesh, or good men who are being judged for heresy, or
          the Bishops or their company about them, or poor men for not paying their duty to their
          Ordinary or their Official. This means wicked doers and pernicious men. <name>Saint Paul</name> said,
          <quote>“If any man that is called a brother is a whore hunter, a covetous person, an idolater, a
          flaunderer, a drunkard, or a thief, do not eat with him. <name>Saint Augustine</name> admitted that
          it is best to have moderation in punishment. Then when the punishment is done, ministers
          must be careful that the church is edified, not distracted. This distraction/fear may seem
          vain, but it is not."</quote> The <name>same Apostle</name> who commanded the incestuous adulterer to be
          delivered to Satan said later in the <ref>Epistle to the Corinthians</ref>, <quote>“I fear that when I come
          I won’t find you as I would, and I will mourn for many that have offended before and have
          not repented themselves of their uncleanliness, from whoring and wantonness."</quote> <name>Saint Paul</name>
          truly threatened them and meant that he would not spare them and would instead deliver
          them to Satan (as he did with adulterers), but because he thought that this harsh
          treatment would lead to the bitter destruction and overthrow of the Church rather than the
          gathering together and the increase of its size, instead he used moderation according to
          God’s commandment. <name>Saint Paul</name> said, <quote>“Do not let both of them grow. If you pull up the
          cockle, you also must pull the wheat up by its roots. It is necessary therefore to use
          holy judgement so that the least offense is committed either by favoring the offender too
          much, or by using too much extremity. Let speedy reconciliation <!--1132.xml-->
          <!-- 1102.xml -->
          <pb ed="#L" n="1132"/>
          <cb ed="#L" n="a"/> Be the driving force among those who are truly repentant."</quote> <name>Saint Paul</name>
          said, <quote>“It is sufficient that certain men are blamed or chided.”</quote> <name>Saint Peter</name>, who
          shamefully denied to Lord, heard the women on the day of the resurrection. <ref>The Gospel</ref> was
          preached by Angels. Moreover, we showed that there is a magistrate in the church, and
          there is authority to execute the sword upon evil doers. To respect his office, a
          magistrate must judge and exercise the sword, he must be a true member of the church.
          These magistrates are necessary to the church. We discuss this in the <ref>7th and 8th sermons
          of the second Decade</ref>. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e5063"> The special institutions and ordinances that God
          appointed for the church are these that follow. Marriage is one of the most important
          institutions of the church because if it is well ordered, it will bear good fruit for the
          church. However, if marriage is not well organized, it can breed endless offenses and
          deadly mischiefs in the church. They judge uprightly. This is to say that the church
          is the most holy and the best assembled when it is gathered together from many
          well-ordered houses. Again, when a church is assembled from many wicked houses, it will be
          a wicked church. Therefore, God in his holy word diligently appoints couples, and
          garnishes wedlock beautifully. However, we are not here to praise matrimony. It suffices
          to know that God himself is the author of marriage, and that he instituted it first in
          Paradise. He did it to this end, so that man would live well and pleasantly with a fellow.
          In conclusion, God coupled a man and a woman together, and being coupled <!--1132.xml-->
          <!--1102.xml-->
          <cb ed="#L" n="b"/> He blessed them. God intended that the most holy friends of God, the
          Patriarchs, Princes, Prophets, Kings, Bishops, wise men and Priests live this kind of
          life. <name>Saint Paul</name> said, <quote>“Wedlock is honorable among all men. It makes the bed undefiled.”</quote>
          In another place, <name>Saint Paul</name> calls the doctrine that forbids wedlock the <quote>“doctrine of
          devils.”</quote> We know that Christ’s Disciples and the Apostles were married men. Neither did
          they put away their wines when they decided to become preachers, although some shamefully
          pretended that they did. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e5173"> We should note that the Apostle requires that one husband
          only has one spouse, and one wife only has one spouse at the hands of a bishop or an
          elder. In another place the Apostle said that, <quote>“it is lawful to have a Christian wife
          while participating in the calling of the Apostleship.”</quote> The Apostle notes how this was a
          challenge both to himself and to <name>Barnabas</name>. At the Council of Nice, the attendants declared
          that to lie with a man’s own wife is equivalent to Chastity. <name>Saint Paul</name> said before, <quote>“Let
          every man have his own wife to avoid fornication.”</quote> He also said, <quote>“The bed of wedlock is
          undefiled”</quote> and, <quote>“If a virgin marries, she does not offend.”</quote> Therefore, we judge Papistical
          doctrine that forbids marriage to ministers to be what <name>the blessed Apostle Saint Paul</name>
          called <quote>“the doctrine of devils.”</quote> The very Papists themselves who have not yet put all
          shamefulness away will confess it with us. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e5247"> If we judge the tree by the fruits, what fruits of single
          life can we recognize? What filthiness, what unchastity, what adulteries, what
          fornications, what ravishings, what incests and heinous copulations can we recognize? <!--1133.xml-->
          <pb ed="#L" n="1133"/>
          <cb ed="#L" n="a"/> Who at this bay lived in a way more unchaste or dishonest than the
          group of priests and monks? They have no regard for God’s word and they do not obey his
          laws. They do not glorify God with a holy life in chaste wedlock: still, God desires to be
          in their hearts. However, they have given themselves up to uncleanliness and now their
          bodies are stained with reproach. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e5291"> Firstly, the holy scripture diligently teaches that all
          men should take special care that they have enter a matrimony that is devout, holy, sober,
          wise, lawful and in the fear of God. The scripture teaches this so that no evil
          disposition of covetousness, desire of promotion, or lust leads men into wedlock.
          Scripture indicates that a man should not enter into wedlock unless the Laws of man or God
          will permit. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e5317"> We must consider the degrees of blood relationship and
          affinity, public honesty and the reverence of blood, of offense towards another so that no
          man takes a wife who is a heathen woman, or a woman of a contrary religion. We are
          expressly forbidden to yoke ourselves with unbelievers. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e5339"> We are taught to enter into the knot of wedlock lawfully,
          divinely, and holily with prayer and the receipt of godly blessing in the temple of the
          lord, both in the fight and with the prayer of the whole congregation. We must beware that
          in any case, we are not stained from the profanation of the filthy world. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e5361"> We should not be ignorant in the case of marriage. Men of
          this world commonly want to celebrate their weddings in a way that is more fit for the
          Devil than for God. Men was to celebrate with rioting, pride, indulgence, drunkenness, and
          wantonness. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e5379">
          <!--1133.xml-->
          <!-- 1103.xml -->
          <cb ed="#L" n="b"/> We are taught to dwell with our wives with knowledge, moderation,
          patience, faith and love. We are also taught to raise our children virtuously and
          honestly, and when the time comes, to place them in holy wedlock. If for adultery or
          another matter more heinous than that, necessity forces one person to break wedlock, the
          church will do nothing without proper advising. The Church has her judges in matters
          and causes of matrimony according to right and equity, or rather according to God’s laws
          and the rule of honesty. <name>The holy Apostle</name> would not have the faithful stand in a court of
          a law in the court of the unfaithful. <name>The holy Apostle</name> exhorts them to take time to make
          friendly agreements between them that were contentious. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e5435"> Regarding matrimony, there are far greater matters that
          forbid the parties that sue or who are sued to come before unbelieving judges. In that
          respect, the Church of God has appointed a Court to try matters of matrimony. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e5453"> Because we already spoke of wedlock in the <ref>tenth sermon
          of the second Decade</ref> and have put forth a book concerning marriage, I have summarized
          Christian wedlock in few words in this sermon. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e5471"> The Church of God has widows in its congregation. <name>The
          Apostle of Christ</name> describes this group of women by saying: <quote>“She that is a widow and a lone
          woman indeed, trusts in God and continues in prayer and supplication night and day. The
          women that live in pleasures and delights is dead though she is still alive.”</quote> <name>The same
          Apostle Paul</name> suggests that younger people marry and have children and govern their own
          houses. <!--1134.xml-->
          <!-- 1104.xml -->
          <pb ed="#L" n="1134"/>
          <cb ed="#L" n="a"/> It is evident in <ref>chapter five of the first epistle of <name>Saint Paul</name> to
          <name>Timothie</name></ref> that he also says that married young people should not allow their enemies to
          speak evil of them. The church also has virgins. Take care so that virgin persons who long
          for the Lord are true virgins without deceit or hypocrisy. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e5536"> <name>Paul</name> said, <quote>“A virgin cares for what belongs to God, she
          may be holy in both body and spirit.”</quote> There are many rules that govern their bodies but
          not their minds; God requires both, especially a chaste mind. It is easy to deceive men,
          but we cannot by any means deceive God. <name>Saint Paul</name> in <ref>the first Epistle to the Corinthians
          in the seventh chapter</ref> sets forth the praise of virginity by comparing a virgin to a
          married wife, he showed how great the goodness of virginity is. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e5577"> It is lawful for virgins to marry if they want. T<name>he same
          Apostles</name> plainly shows this in the same place in the <ref>Scriptures</ref>. Unto this testimony of
          God the testimony of man also is agreeable. <name>Cyprian</name> and his fellow Bishops and Elders,
          answered a demand from <name>Pomponius</name> by saying, <quote>“Do you want us to write to you what we think
          of virgins, who after they once determined to continue their chaste state steadfastly, are
          found to have lied and still lay in the same bed with men? You do desire to know our
          judgement, and you will understand that we do not depart from the traditions and
          ordinances of the <ref>Gospel</ref> and the Apostles. We should less strongly and stoutly provide for
          our brethren and sisters so that ecclesiastical discipline should be kept by all means for
          their profit <!--1134.xml-->
          <!-- 1104.xml -->
          <cb ed="#L" n="b"/> and safety.”</quote> They continued, <quote>“If through faith, they have vowed
          themselves to Christ and continue chastely, and modestly, let them stoutly look for the
          reward of virginity. But if they will not or cannot continue, it is better that they marry
          than to fall into the fire of their desires and pleasures."</quote> <name>Saint Augustine</name> disputed the
          words of the Apostle. <name>Augustine</name> said that <quote>“virgins who choose to marry instead of
          remaining in the convent face a greater damnation because they broke their first promise.”</quote>
          His message means that one former nun who later married should not ascribe this damnation
          to the marriage following, but to the inconsistency that occurred before. <name>Augustine</name>
          continued, <quote>“Such are damned not because they entered into the bond and promise of wedlock,
          but because they broke the first promise they made with self-restraint and chastity.”</quote> Soon
          after this passage, <name>Augustine</name> added the following: <quote>“They say that such marriages are not
          marriages but rather adulteries. It seems to me that they speak foolishly and without
          consideration.”</quote> I understand that by this word, condemnation and judgement is what the
          Apostle Reprehension which we Switzers term, <foreign>“Ein anszricten order nachred”</foreign> meant. Many
          speak poorly about former nuns who break their first promise, that is to say they have
          broken the promise of chastity. However, the Apostle thinks it is much better for young
          women to find a partner in marriage than to force themselves into such an order of life
          from which they cannot depart without serious reprehension of men. However, in that
          place the Apostle is speaking not about virgins but about widows. <name>Saint Cyprian</name> spoke
          simply about virgins. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e5765"> Monks and nuns were altogether unknown in the primitive <!--1135.xml-->
          <!-- 1105.xml -->
          <pb ed="#L" n="1135"/>
          <cb ed="#L" n="a"/> Church of Christ, and the Apostles of the later ages had monks, but
          they were nothing like what we have now. Monks now have their own rule and law, and their
          monasteries are filled with filthiness and uncleanliness. Although we should hold our
          peace yet to be true, truth and experience are sufficient for now. The monasteries that
          seem to govern with more severe discipline are still defiled with hypocrisy. I will let
          this subject rest now. The first monks lived in cities, but they still did not involve
          themselves in worldly affairs. In another location among these sermons, we have discussed
          how a writer during the middle ages could not be a clerk and an Abbot. There is a conflict
          of interest when holding a position as a clerk and an Abbot, one is an impediment to the
          other. Clerks who are also abbots lived not from the common revenues of the church, but of
          their own wealth. They used their own money to travel as lay people do. </p>
        <p> <name>Saint Jerome</name> disputed the existence of the original monks in the life of <name>Paulus</name>, and he
          wrote: <quote>“Among many different people it has been called into question who first began
          chiefly to dwell in the wilderness as a monk? Some people who answer are far off and they
          begin to reckon that <name>Helias the holy Prophet</name> and <name>Saint John</name> were monks. But <name>Helias</name> seemed
          to us to have been more than a monk, and <name>Saint John</name> began to prophecy before he was born.
          But others, (with whom most people commonly agree) affirm that <name>Saint Antonie</name> began the
          order, which in part is true. He was not only the first, but also the motioner of all
          others. <name>Amathas</name> and <name>Macharius</name>, Saint Antonie’s scholars who were the first to bury their
          master’s body do affirm that <!--1135.xml-->
          <!-- 1105.xml -->
          <cb ed="#L" n="b"/> <name>Paulus Thebius</name> was the one who began the monkhood. We can confirm that
          not only in name but also in opinion.</quote> He added that <name>Paulus</name> forsook the city that was
          forced under the persecutors <name>Decius</name> and <name>Valerianus</name> because of fear of torment. <name>Paulus</name>
          departed into the wilderness where he found a cave and lay hidden until he was found by
          <name>Saint Antonie</name>. The <name>Emperors Decius</name> and <name>Valerianus</name> governed the empire during the year of
          the Lord in 260 A.D., but it is said that <name>Saint Antonie</name> died when he was 105 years old, in
          the year of our Lord 360 A.D. In his <ref>80th epistle to <name>Helychius</name></ref>, <name>Saint Augustine</name> witnessed
          that he lived in the year of the Lord, 430 A.D. But, <name>Eutropius</name> and <name>Beda</name> reported how he
          died in the year of our Lord 430 in the <ref>thirty first chapter of the manners of the
          Catholic church</ref>. <name>Eutropius</name> and <name>Beda</name> recited the manners and institutions of the monks in
          his time and reported such things as are very far from the orders and institutions of
          monks now a days. During his reign, <name>Justinian the Emperor</name> made certain laws for Monks and
          monasteries. At one point, <name>Benet</name> lived in a monastery, and now the monks call him Father.
          I will discuss <name>Benet</name>’s life from the Trittenheymium, who died fifty years since, with the
          intent that you may understand what power and dignity they obtained in the process of
          time. At the beginning, these men did not have authority. <quote>“<name>Benet Abbat of Caffina</name>”</quote> he
          said, <quote>“beginner and governor of the monks in the west wrote eloquently and with grave
          judgement the rule for Monks in one book, which begins, <!--1136.xml-->
          <!-- 1106.xml -->
          <pb ed="#L" n="1136"/>
            <cb ed="#L" n="a"/> listen to my precepts.”</quote> It contained seventy-three chapters. He died
          in the year of our Lord 542 A.D. But, <name>Marianus Scotus</name> supposed that he died in the year of
          our Lord 601 A.D., the last year of <name>Emperor Mauric</name>’s reign. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e6099"> He also wrote twenty orders for monks who were under
          <name>Benet</name>’s rule. During <name>Saint Benet</name>’s rule, there were eighteen popes in the Sea of Rome,
          over 200 cardinals, 1500 Archbishops in various churches, and nearly 4000 bishops. There
          were about 15,700 abbots who excelled in writing and doctrine of which about 15,500 are
          canonized. I will not recite the many other orders of monks because it is well known that
          the mendicant monks and Friars are faithful, diligent and valiant Roman champions of the
          pope. The spiritual monarchy was confirmed by <name>Honorrus</name> around the year of our Lord 1222
          A.D. I will not declare anything else but only that men should understand that the
          monkhood was man’s invention, and it was not delivered to the Church of Christ by the
          Apostles. At first it seemed to be tolerable, but afterward it became intolerable. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e6174"> Now, it is profitable to the commonwealth because it
          taught its experience. Whoever knows that it is repugnant to true religion knows
          nothing. They feign that it is meritorious before God and the state of perfection. Who
          doesn’t see how repugnant it is to Christ’s merit and to the sincere doctrine of the
          Gospel? What <!--1136.xml-->
          <!-- 1106.xml -->
          <cb ed="#L" n="b"/> Godliness or necessity is it that moves us after we have wholly given
          ourselves to one god in baptism, to give ourselves and to make vows to Saints, and to
          blind ourselves by religion of another by observing their rules? True religion forbids us
          from bowing to Saints or in any way depending upon them in religion. </p>
        <p> True religion forbids us to choose any other Fathers or Masters than our one God. True
          religion forbids us to devise new ways of worship, or new religions, or to receive those
          that are devised by others. Let us look at the example of <name>Jeroboam</name> and his fellows. This
          example should make us afraid. True religion forbids us to swear by the names of other
          Gods. Religion refers us to one God by faith and obedience. Superstition breaks this band
          and admits creatures. <name>Saint Paul</name> to the Corinthians said, <quote>“Every one of you says, I am
          <name>Paul</name>’s, I am <name>Apollo</name>’s, I am <name>Cephaes</name>’, and I am Christ’s. Is Christ divided? Was Paul
          crucified for you? Or were you baptized in the name of <name>Paul</name>?”</quote> Behold, Christ is our
          redeemer and our master. The faith of Christ has made us one body. By baptism, we are
          baptized into one body so that we are called Christians, not Petrines or Paulines. <name>Saint
          Paul</name> would not suffer that Christians should take the name of their Apostles, how much
          less would he abide that at this day some should be called Benedictines, some Franciscans,
          some Dominicans. We are the Lord’s inheritance and possession: it is now lawful for us to
          bind ourselves to the service of men. Whoever binds themselves to men tears the unity of
          Christ’s body, they prophane the cross and the baptism of Christ. <!--1137.xml-->
          <!-- 1107.xml -->
          <pb ed="#L" n="1137"/>
          <cb ed="#L" n="a"/> <name>The Apostle</name> said plainly, <quote>“Is Christ divided? Was Paul crucified for
          you, or were you baptized in the name of <name>Paul</name>?”</quote> Therefore, although people call them
          spiritual, they are nothing less than spiritual. <name>The Apostle</name> said, <quote>“When one of you said,
          ‘I am <name>Paul</name>’s,’ and ‘I <name>Apollo</name>’s,’ are you not carnal?”</quote> After you receive the Gospel of
          Christ and the doctrine of the Apostles which contains and delivers godliness to us, to
          what end do you need to invent new rules? When people once found out certain peculiar laws
          and ways of life, they separated themselves from the common fort of
          Christians in all outward manners of living. They differentiated themselves in their
          behavior, their apparel with the intent to show all men that they would live apart. They
          did this to distance themselves from the common lay people and the imperfect church so
          they could live a more holy, perfect, and spiritual life. However well you describe them,
          the whole world speaks it to this day. The vows that they promise are foolish. They bow to
          chastity and they are not chaste. Chastity is a gift from God, and it is not possible for
          all men. <name>Saint Paul</name> said, <quote>“Whoever cannot live chastely and modestly, let him marry. It is
          better to marry than to burn.”</quote> Generally, <name>Saint Paul</name> said to burn, whether it was in or
          out of a vow. The vow of chastity is unlawful and inhumane when foolishly taken in hand
          and vowed, and it prejudices the law of God. <quote>“What manner of poverty it is which is in
          Abbeys, experience itself teaches.”</quote> In Abbeys, there is a level of poverty that
          through experiences, teaches the monks how to behave. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e6445"> Monks put off poverty when they wear their common
          garments and put on great riches (? 45). <!--1137.xml-->
          <!-- 1107.xml> -->
          <cb ed="#L" n="b"/> Monks are made princes, even though in the old time this would have
          seemed strange and monstrous. Most of them live idly and eat their bread freely and for
          nothing, against the Apostle’s rule in <quote>chapter three of the second Epistle to the
          Thessalonians</quote>. They are cursed. They forsake their parents and kinsfolk, by whom God’s law
          they are bound to serve and obey. They deliver themselves to strange men and they are
          forced to infinite superstitions. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e6492"> They are then set free from their parents, either from
          superstition or with the intent that they may have all the days of their life to lie and
          rot in idleness. It is evident that these monks wear riches not for any religion. What
          obedience is that which is contrary to the obedience that is revealed by the word of God?
          When the magistrate commanded them to sustain and hear public burdens with the faithful,
          they were more free and exempted from work. During the old time, ministers of strange religions
          under the Kings of Juda had princely privileges and customs confirmed by the long
          prescription of time. But their ministry was not allowed by the word of God, it was
          repugnant to the word of God. They were not ungodly, or unjustly or sacrilegiously broken
          and divorced by holy kings. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e6549"> Who genuinely hears this excuse? Who is admonished to do
          penance for the sins for which they have committed? Who makes this exception, that by
          virtue of their other they are referred to a monkish order so that with safe
          conscience they can continue to sin? It is evident that <!--1138.xml-->
          <pb ed="#L" n="1138"/>
          <cb ed="#L" n="a"/> the other that they pretend is a rash other should not be performed. I
          have declared this in the <ref>third sermon of the second Decade</ref>. What can a band made by man
          without God, rather by man against the word of God, do? Especially if it was made
          unwisely? If the Cross of Christ is of such great virtue that it has released us from the
          curse of original sin which we were all subject, how much more will it deliver us? We were
          entrapped in outward bonuses/rewards not by God, but through folly or wickedness of man,
          or through the craft of the devil </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e6614"> The <name>Apostle Saint Paul</name> cried out, <quote>“You were bought for a
          price, you may not become servants of me.”</quote> If we happily become servants through malice or
          our own folly, God must endeavor that through true faith and obedience liberty is restored
          to the children of God. The Gospel is preached to us with the intent that we should be
          delivered from any unjust captivity so that we may serve God in spirit and truth. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e6647"> Moreover, some people may object our argument against
          monasteries. They may say that it was good and convenient that monasteries throughout the
          world were reformed and brought back to simplicity. We will answer that in our unhappy
          age, this reform was in vain and it is plain folly to hope for it. Monasteries cannot be
          reduced to ancient simplicity. Neither will princes and monks suffer any such reformation.
          They know that if they did suffer a reformation, they would part with their profits,
          honors and pleasures altogether. They would prefer that the whole world was gathered
          together by the ears than rather if they had to deliver up to God his kingdom. <!--1138.xml-->
          <!-- 1108.xml -->
          <cb ed="#L" n="b"/> which they have materially enjoyed. Is it easy enough to persuade us
          that if Abbeys were reformed according to the ancient institution, in this age would they
          be well or better governed? Who would persuade us? Now that we see what beginning they
          had, how they have gone forward and how they have increased, we see what hypocrisy,
          ambition, covetousness, pleasure, and idleness can do, and to what point all things come.
          Do we think that today, man’s desires will be more moderate? Do we think that discipline
          will not be as corrupted by our posterity than it was by our forefathers? We are
          constrained not to hope for the better, but rather to fear for the worst. Every day there
          are experiments as to what is worse than another. We live in the dregs of the world in the
          latter end of all ages, in the dragon of the bottomless pit where the malice and
          ungodliness of men has procured great power and force so they may disturb and corrupt all
          things that are in the entire world. How is it that in such great perils, this comforts
          us? Not even a little is written in the word of truth. For the elect’s sake, those days
          are shortened. They will be loose for a short time, and then they will be cast into the
          lake that burns with fire and brimstone. If we make a just reformation, we need to go to
          the fountains themselves. In the primitive church, we do not read anything set down in the
          <ref>doctrine of Christ and his Apostles</ref> concerning abbeys and monks. Thereby, we understand
          that it is not necessary for the church. We have learned by experience that it is hurtful
          to the Church. </p>
        <p>
          <!--1139.xml-->
          <!-- 1109.xml -->
          <pb ed="#L" n="1139"/>
          <cb ed="#L" n="a"/> True reformation persuades us altogether to abrogate abbeys and monks.
          We will not reject them meanly. The church will gently receive those who repent the
          wickedness of the time into the care and alms of the church. We have said this on occasion
          before. Concerning abbeys and monks, which we have declared to have had no place in the
          primitive Church of Christ and his Apostles, let us return to other necessary institutions
          of the Church. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e6832"> The faithful church of Christ uses discipline regarding
          the sick and dying. Neighbors and brethren should gather around them, and everyone should
          partake in their duty of love and charity. These acts of love and charity relieve the
          needy with goodness, and if the sick are not needy, neighbors and brethren show other
          duties of good will. The minister of the church also comes to comfort the sick person and
          prepare him for death. First, the person makes his confession of sins to God. The minister
          pronounces out of the word of God that the sick person be forgiven if he is faithful. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e6869"> The minister requires the person to forgive, to be in
          love and charity with all men, and to keep no grudge or malice in his heart. After this,
          the sick person makes a public prayer to God, and those that are in his party know that he
          is at the point of death. He is admonished of sundry things, confirmed in the faith,
          called to patience. He is instructed according to his goods and everything else that is
          required, and he is taught that at his departing of the world, he commend his soul into
          the hands of God the father according <!--1139.xml-->
          <!-- 1109.xml -->
          <cb ed="#L" n="b"/> to the doctrine and example of our redeemer, who at the very point of
          death cried aloud and said, <quote>“Father into thy hands I commend my spirit.”</quote> </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e6920"> We have learned this discipline from the Apostles of our
          Lord Christ. <name>The Apostle Saint James</name> said, <quote>“If any are sick among you, let him send for
          the elders of the church and let them pray over him, anointing him with oil in the name of
          the Lord. The prayer which is made in faith will deliver the sick. The Lord will raise him
          up again.”</quote> </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e6949"> <quote>“If he is in sin, the elders will forgive him. Confess
          your sins to another and pray one for another that you will be safe. The hearty prayer of
          the just is of great force.”</quote> This is the apostolic discipline. If you said to me, ‘Where
          is the oil?’ I answer that in Saint J<name>ames the Apostle</name>’s time, and for years later, there
          remained in the church the miraculous gift of healing the sick. We read this in <ref><name>Saint
          Mark</name>’s Gospel</ref> which says, <quote>“And the disciples going forth preached the Gospel so that they
          might repent. They cast out many devils, and they anointed many with oil and healed the
          sick.”</quote> And again in the same place he said, <quote>“Moreover, these signs will follow those that
          believe. In my name they will cast out devils.”</quote> He said, <quote>“They will lay their hands upon
          the sick and they will be healed.”</quote> Because this benefit remained in the Church, <name>Saint
          James</name> bid us to use oil and to use it in the name of the Lord, as the Lord had commanded.
          We see that the gift has ceased in the church. We find by experience that oil does no good
          to the sick, according to our time, and as our duty binds us, we do the best we… <!--1140.xml-->
          <!-- 1110.xml -->
          <pb ed="#L" n="1140"/>
          <cb ed="#L" n="a"/> can assuage and cure the sick with medicines that are currently used
          and applied in the name of Christ. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e7057"> By this testimony of the Apostle, the Papists try to
          validate their extreme beliefs, but they labor in vain. <name>Saint James</name> did not say anything
          about hallowed oil. They did not use this medicine except in extreme circumstances where
          <name>Saint James</name> commanded that every sick person get anointed. How can they [the papists]
          defend words from <name>Saint James</name> that of which the priest demanded of the sick person? He
          said, <quote>“Do you believe that the Lord will hear our prayers for their merit’s sake, and
          prayers for the saints?”</quote> The sick man answered and said, <quote>“I do believe.”</quote> He then said,
          <quote>“Let us pray to God and his Saints.”</quote> Or should I suggest you pray to <name>Saint James</name> or any
          other Apostle of Christ that was taught how to anoint? He continued, <quote>“In the name of the
          father, and of the son, and of the holy Ghost, I anoint you with holy oil so that with
          this anointing you may receive full remission from your sins.”</quote> What scripture I ask,
          teaches us that the full remission of sins can be obtained through anointing? These things
          are done against the principle article of our religion that teaches us that we are purged
          from all our sins only by the blood of Christ, and only by that most fully. To Christ only
          is the glory due, not to the oil, nor to any creature in the world. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e7155"> The Church of Christ does not reject bodies of the dead,
          as if they were dead animals. This Church acknowledges that their bodies were Temples of
          the Holy Ghost that dwelled in them during life. I acknowledge <!--1140.xml-->
          <cb ed="#L" n="b"/>that they are buried in hope of resurrection and the glory of life
          everlasting. In a reverent manner, some people take the bodies and wrap them in a sheet to
          cover them decently. Then, they are put into the coffin carefully, and they are carried to
          their place of burial in the churchyard near friends, neighbors and brethren. Friends,
          neighbors and brethren follow after to accompany the corpse as well. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e7199"> While the body is set down and laid in the earth, there
          are public prayers made by those who brought the corpse. They thank God for calling the
          deceased out of this world and into the true faith. They pray in hopes that it pleases the
          Lord to take the dead speedily so that they may be lightened with the true faith. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e7223"> The name of the dead whether they are brother or sister
          is recited in the public assembly of the church with honor. All the people there are put
          in mind of their own destiny so that they may speedily prepare themselves to die. After
          this, we read from the scriptures that the ancient fathers buried their dead, including
          the most holy of them. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e7245"> The ancient fathers do not canonize or worship relics for
          months or years after death. When the soul is suffered to depart, they will be delivered
          to painful purgatory. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e7261"> Certain burials like those of <name>Abraham</name>, <name>Sara</name>, <name>Isaac</name>,
          <name>Jacob</name>, <name>Joseph</name>, <name>Aaron</name>, <name>Marie</name>, <name>Joshua</name>, <name>Samuel</name>, and </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e7318"> <name>Joseph</name>’s bones were carried forth in a mystery. <!--1141.xml-->
          <!-- 1111.xml -->
          <pb ed="#L" n="1141"/>
          <cb ed="#L" n="a"/> His bones were put forth in mystery so the Israelites could gather
          them and bring them to the land of promise. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e7341"> The patriarchs chose a burial in Hebron. The place itself
          doesn’t have much meaning besides the speed that the body is buried. It is justified to
          think that the places where saints and holy men are buried is sanctified or holy, but
          bodies do not become holy by being placed into the ground. Therefore, unless it seems
          better otherwise to the divine providence of God, the Saints would gladly lie with their
          ancestors in the same place of burial. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e7378"> If it pleases God otherwise, at least they are still
          received into the same earth. Without any exception, they are not separated from their
          ancestors because of the distance between where they are buried. There is no superstition
          in the Church of God about burials and graves. There was a lot of superstition in the time
          of the Papists, so much that one man cannot describe it in few words. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e7404"> These are the necessary institutions of the Church of
          God. The faithful religiously observes these institutions without superstition to edify
          the Church. Other matters that are devised by man are not godly. I know what things some
          people may object here. Moving on, the <ref>Old Testament</ref> had many rites and ceremonies
          instituted on behalf of God by his holy Prophets because they needed instruction. However,
          since the common Christians are more ignorant, they created so many <!--1141.xml-->
          <!-- 1111.xml -->
          <cb ed="#L" n="b"/>diverse ceremonies. The Ancient fathers only created with the motion
          of the spirit that they obeyed. This is not a reason to justify the weak in faith
          receiving commodities. The Apostles of Christ would not have justified that. Experience
          teaches us that the state and the condition of the weak and simpleminded is such that more
          ceremonies are left to them. Their minds become more diverse, dispersed, and united to
          Christ, to whom alone all things are ascribed. It pleased the father that fullness should
          dwell in him. He heaped together all things pertaining to our life and salvation in him.
          The divine wisdom of God takes away the external discipline and instruction between us and
          them. Therefore, we should proceed to bring Judaism again if we intend not stop
          multiplying rites and ceremonies according to the Olde Church. In the old time, those
          ceremonies that we used were not finite. They were comprised to occur within a certain
          number. At this present, there is no place or use for them in the church. We should not
          want a grave authority to prove it. The Apostles and Elders in a great assembly met in
          Jerusalem, and the Apostle told them that they tempt the Lord to lay the law upon the
          ‘free neckers’ of the Christians. Therefore, a Synodal Epistle was written and the
          Apostles and Elders testified that it seemed good to the Holy Ghost to not burden the
          Church of Christ. They then decided to recite few words. <!--1142.xml-->
          <!-- 1112.xml -->
          <pb ed="#L" n="1142"/>
          <cb ed="#L" n="a"/> The doctrine of the Gospel is sufficient for the Church without the
          ceremonies of the law. If people do not want to unite rites from the old time instituted
          by god with the Gospel, then we should not want to couple the Gospel with the inventions
          of men. Which do you think is more wicked? Thus for the preparation for the grace and
          worship of God or salvation, we cannot say less than <name>Saint Paul</name> said long ago: <quote>“After you
          have known God, how could you return to weak and beggarly ways? Why wouldn’t you begin to
          serve in a new way? You observe days, months, times and years. I am afraid I have taken
          the pain to help you in vain."</quote> He added, <quote>“Unto all these things, we must also address the
          instruction of ceremonies. These ceremonies belong to the worship of God, but we are
          forbidden to devise for ourselves <!--1142.xml-->
          <cb ed="#L" n="b"/>Strange worship. We are forbidden to put anything in or take anything
          from our institution or the Word of God.</quote> Therefore, the Church of God does not deny or
          receive any such constitutions. We have spoken about this before when we discussed the
          abrogation of the law, and of Christian liberty. </p>
        <p xml:id="UD1xh4-7yMcbW-d1e7636"> I trust that in these fifty sermons, I have shortly and
          conveniently as I could have, comprehended the whole matter of faith, godliness, or true
          religion and of the Church. That which I write in my books I probably repeat in the
          Decades. I hope that the learned will gather and embrace the scriptures because of my good
          will and thanks. To the Lord our God, everlasting fountain of goodness, I hope there is
          praise and glory through our Lord Jesus Christ. Amen. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
